[Music]
the following is a production of Frankie
Freitas and the internet Museum of
hologography
[Music]
hello and welcome to another week of
holotalk for the week of March
15th I believe it is I don't have the
calendar handy with me here right now
but I believe it's the week of March
15th a greetings from the blizzard
capital of the United States or at least
the next day or two is going to be the
blizzard capital of the United States
Allentown Pennsylvania the snow's coming
down we're expecting what we call here
on the east coast and lower Eastern
which is going to give us a potential of
several feet of snow and if you haven't
seen Allentown Pennsylvania and tuning
in on Sunday night or perhaps even
Monday it's Sunday night now here the
weather channel has a reporter in
Allentown Pennsylvania so when you turn
on the Weather Channel and get updates
on this winter storm you will be able to
look right into the town of holotalk in
my studio so greetings to everyone of
course it's always nice to see the snow
coming down but boy
shoveling that we're going to have to do
when this mess is over is going to be
incredible
fortunately by the middle of the week
we're going to be up into the mid to
Upper 60s
so it's not going to hang around as if
it had hit earlier in the year like
December or January which should be
around for months
so it's going to be a nice night great
night to do Holograms if you've ever
done Holograms you know that there's
nothing better to dampen vibration in
your environment to have a nice color of
snow on the ground and no cars running
around on the street becomes very quiet
this week we have Steve Michael as our
guest and if you're logging on to listen
to his fantastic story you're in for a
real treat I know when I opened his
email my jaw hit the desk I just
believe that
all this is happening with such an
inexpensive way to make Holograms with
laser pointers and Steve's going to be
on in just a second to tell us all about
this hologram he made to have some depth
of of seven and a half feet
which I believe works out to about two
and a half meters
I'm real familiar with uh nanometers and
millimeters milliliters and liters but
when it gets up into meters and
kilometers I'm a little a little touchy
on that so I think it's about two and a
half meters in
reach out to seven and a half feet the
U.S feet
in any case Steve is going to be one to
tell us all about it and also a few tips
on processing the slavage materials as
well a few things that he's found out
working with those materials and let me
tell you
this is absolutely an incredible story
about this depth that he's received in
this hologram because number one there's
no indication that this is the upper
limit I remember when we first started
talking that we thought it was an
incredible feat a few inches and I did
the eight by ten hologram which had a
piece of coral that went back into the
Hologram about eight inch depth and that
was incredible and it continued on and
on but when you talk about seven and a
half feet now folks we're not talking
about a very expensive laser system like
a water cooled argon that has an edelon
attached to it that allows it to record
a great amount of depth that's running
in the tens of thousands of dollars
folks we're talking about a little
battery powered
laser pointer for 14.99 and this was a
split being laser transmission hologram
that he made and been quite by mistake
actually uh not by mistake but by chance
a lot of the strayed light actually went
past the scene that he had set up he set
up a little scene of the lunar lander
module with some astronauts on the
surface of the Moon things like that and
he noticed that the uh well I'll let him
talk tell you about it because there's
an incredible part of the story and
maybe he should tell you about it as
well and before I tell you and we'll
just go in and listen to a thing but in
any case
uh also if you have an opportunity to
check out my shoebox holography page
which is a little tiny system that I've
put together for introducing children
school-aged children to holography using
laser pointers it all fits in the area
the size of the shoe box and it's also
great for demonstrating holography at
museums or schools even for doing
workshops and what's nice about it is
this like I had mentioned this whole
system packs up into the area the size
of the shoe box and
because the laser pointer is battery
operated you do not need to even be
around electricity to make the Hologram
so that's an interesting aspect of it as
well
so let's move on the interview with
Steve I think runs about 15 minutes or
so and I'm not going to come back on
after it's over I just want to get this
finished up here run out and grab
something to eat and get back and
probably do a little bit of shoveling
after I get this up and I want to thank
you for tuning in to whole talk and
continue to tune in each and every week
when we bring you news information on
lasers and holography and also some late
breaking news
that if not for the internet would be
virtually impossible to get as quickly
as you're getting this right now because
I got this email
probably around lunchtime today from
Steve and through the magic of the
internet within hours I have this up
with an interview on the web that
everyone
get information about it so then I'm
going to me now this is my own personal
opinion
to me because I don't want anyone saying
that I've lost my mind or this or that I
feel that this is one of the most
incredible Holograms
ever made
and the reason being is because we see a
lot of deep Holograms that are made with
systems that run into tens of thousands
of dollars and with very expensive laser
systems and
Optical components and Arrangements
but this is something that's completely
different and it's I see a shift in
holography that almost a revolutionary
shift in the field of holography and
even though we're still what many
high-end holographers would consider low
end holography
I see it having an impact on the upper
end sooner or later as well and
I'm not going to go any further with
that we will let this all unfold in the
way that it needs to unfold but I think
some of the things that are happening
right now are possibly some of the most
important things that have ever happened
in the field of holography certainly
within the last several years at least
if not going back to the beginning but
this hologram by Steve Michael which
shows seven and a half feet of depth
using a 14.99 battery operated laser
pointer with all homemade equipment I
consider myself in my opinion
one of the most
important Holograms that have ever been
created and let's see if my my little
opinion there actually Bears out
of any type of fruit within the next
several weeks several months because
this isn't the end of the line folks
this is not the end of the line this is
still very much the beginning and who
knows where this is going to go and who
knows how long it's going to be maybe a
few weeks or maybe a few months but
considering the holography goes back to
the 60s waiting a few weeks or a few
months for a new
to come through and as a breakthrough is
not that very long so in within the next
few months if we happen to get another
story who knows what the next story is
going to be and how far forward we will
move again and once again I think it's
giving many people
freedom to finally break the chains of
traditional holography which has bound
us to certain sizes and certain things
that we could do certain things that we
couldn't do that only the larger
Research Laboratories could do and we
are definitely breaking out of those
change or chains and we're saying we're
here
and now holography is finally in the
hands of the masses and let's see what
people can do with it and if we can't
take this somewhere so let's move on to
the interview with Steve Michael
like I said before I'm not going to come
back on of course I went on for another
five or ten minutes after I said that
but I I've just been I've just been so
excited all day long about this and you
know dry driving around I couldn't stop
thinking about it I was grinding my
teeth sitting at red lights just
thinking about how exciting that this is
so um congratulations to Steve Michael
and what he's doing for holography
cannot be put into words believe me so
thanks for tuning in and first
let's have a word
from my sponsor which is my own Studio
because I was I can't get any other
sponsors so I have to sponsor it myself
thanks for tuning in see you next week
would you like to make your own
one-of-a-kind hologram and learn how you
can start making holograms on your own
at the same time you can do this and
much more by attending one of Frankie's
greatest holography workshops from
beginner to Advanced Frank's got a
workshop that's just right for you from
single afternoon evening or weekend
introductory workshops to Wednesday
evening five-week complete courses and
don't forget his newest Workshop laser
pointer holography
located just off the Northeast Extension
of the Pennsylvania Turnpike and
Interstate 78 the studio is a quick
non-stop drive from the New York
Philadelphia and Baltimore Washington DC
areas for more information call the
Studio's toll-free hotline at
1-800-458-3525 and begin your own
Journey with holography today that's
1-800-458-3525 for more information
solography Workshop today
thank you
it's Frankie fries how are you hi Frank
fine I wanted to get you on the phone
and if you don't mind maybe record a
couple of your comments on that hologram
that you made for this week's show the
transmission I made with the death yeah
okay I've already told a few people
about that this is just incredible I
know it blew me away
um I I was really amazed to see that I
could uh all I did was shoot the uh the
object beam just went across the whole
landscape of a lunar lander thing yeah
you know from front to back
and that was uh everything was there no
and Tiffany drop off or anything yeah
which is incredible in itself you know I
I noticed that there was light in the
background on my lab wall I must have
gone I know so seven and a half feet
seven and a half feet
that's incredible um I'm gonna try the
same I'm going to try the same setup
with my 35 milliwatt let's see
you know what it does yeah now is this a
split beam hologram yeah okay yeah good
it's unbelievable
Infinity 200 is fantastic well I imagine
you must be getting a lot of emails like
I am from people who are doing this now
right as a matter of fact I just got one
from this guy he had a pointer and he
was in the sun set up a setup
and they were they weren't getting first
of all they were using
um
pfg01 okay
and they were doing 10 second exposures
and nothing was coming out and it's just
you know pink yeah
so I said well you know you gotta it's
gonna be longer try uh 60 Seconds
so he did and the film did get down but
there was no image
so he said well okay I'm gonna buy the
Infiniti 200 and he did yeah put that in
the system and it looked the first time
well it was just for a reflection of
transmission transmission yeah
what's what exposure times are you
finding compared to agfa with the 01s
and the O3 emulsions I'm finding the old
one to be about twice okay and I'm
finding the all three to be four times
four times well yeah okay so two yeah
four to four times and generally with
the final one like the one the
transmission I did last night they you
know I used the station photo and Ken
Hall came off super clean and it was a
30 second exposure on agfa 8075. what
size plate did you use okay yeah
remember I had that cross effect
on the O3 yeah and I'm finding out the
film is very because it's such a
fine-grained film
it's like Kodak Tech cam film which
needs special agitation with the tech
Tam film what you do is you drop it into
the tech pen developer and you agitate
it
vertically not flipping it over in the
you know the tank yeah
um for five seconds then you let it sit
for 30 seconds
and then in other words you're not doing
this um actually I take that back with
that one you agitate up and down
vertically for two seconds two up and
downs that leather sit for 30 seconds if
you do any more agitation than that what
happens is you get more density around
the edges of the perforation I see
so I I applied the same technique to the
old tree uh instead of flushing the tray
back and forth left to right and up and
down which was actually causing the
cross effects okay it was developing
more depth down the center and across
the center
top to bottom and left to right yeah
because of the way I was walking the
tree so what I did was when I put the
film in I grabbed the corner of the film
and used circular agitation for five
seconds
okay let it sit for 30 seconds
then do another five seconds of circular
rotation let us sit for 30 seconds and
continue doing this for the whole five
minutes and what processing technique
you're using still using yeah just a
straight fiber right yes and the cross
effect disappeared and I got uniform
eliminate um you know density across the
whole piece of film and I just put that
up today on my site if you go to uh my
section uh title film okay dot HTML okay
I describe that technique there okay now
you don't have to do that for zero one
because it's not a fine grain did you
say you ever did a reflection hologram
to zero one yet I don't know I I think I
did but I can't remember okay
because that would be really good if you
if if that is possible with that faster
emulsion right you know
well like I said um
at the most you're looking at two
minutes and oh three
four four by five for four by five with
the infiniter you know and that's the
split D yeah
yeah so the single being on the two and
a half by two and a half plates are I
think it's 50 millimeter by 50
millimeter their sizes would uh cut that
down considerably for kids
again but I'm curious about this uh the
depth on this hologram I mean it's seven
and a half feet that is isn't an
indication at all that we're maxed out
either exactly I mean I can't I mean I
could certainly set something up on my
you know 10-foot table see uh if I can
reach 10 feet
um but have a feeling I will and I want
to go beyond and I can't because I've
maxed it out of course like I said I
couldn't I was amazed that my wall was
absolutely stable during that 30 seconds
yeah that's sort of like I guess with
John player uh probably not as close to
going into the caves you know because he
uses no vibration isolation at all in
the caves but I guess the foundation of
the house that that wall actually part
of the foundation or with the wall in
the middle of the house no it was the
foundation yeah it was outside
Foundation plus I had my kids walking
around upstairs
shedding the microwave turning it off
all during this exposure so and
everything just I mean the whole there
was just beautiful wow are you gonna put
something up on your webpage about that
too yes I am um I need the photograph
first yeah we'll make sure there's a
link on the whole talk page so that
people can go back over again
yeah it's going to take me um I'm
probably not going to shoot the film
until tomorrow night and then processing
I don't have a digital camera but okay
um I should get the results up there by
uh the middle of the week okay so if
you're listening to the show in the
middle of the week the end of the week
you might want to start going over to
Steve's website and see this
what has to be absolutely the most
incredible hologram that's ever been
made I'm going to say that right now
this has to be I don't care if it was a
large corporation that did all the work
that's been done in the past but this is
a 14.99 laser pointer whose man that's
managed to create seven and a half feet
of depth and a whole ground so this this
has got to be one of one of the greatest
not the greatest whole grams that's ever
been made
it's got to be thank you
you know I mean unless We're Dreaming
this no I'm not you know I know you're
for real but I I'm starting to think I'm
losing my mind well you know after being
involved with holograms for so many
years to finally start hearing these
things
um it's uh
to someone who's brand new they probably
say well you know that's cool and move
on you know but anybody who's been doing
this since the 60s and 70s or 80s just
has to you know the jaw has to hit the
desk
right
um and I would appreciate it if you
would go ahead and do the experiment
yourself and back it up yeah okay in
fact we are in a blizzard condition up
in the Allentown area and we're looking
at 16
to 24 inches of snow
through tonight which is a perfect time
to make whole dreams because everything
unusual talk about dampening your
environment right I mean it it's always
so quiet and peaceful right no cars on
the road yeah no cars on the road and
you walk outside and it's just peaceful
and it's a great time to do Holograms
so I'd love to set something up and
shoot this one once I get this show
finished and up on the air you know it
don't let me last night after I saw this
hologram it blows the way the need to
have equal Pathways oh yes absolutely if
you've got that much coherentness right
you don't have to worry about passing
what's the path length we'll be saying
in a couple weeks from now
I'm sorry what was that the baby's
saying that that's a path one you don't
even you know that the whole terminology
may even just drop right out of
holography yeah except for those places
that have shorter coherently yeah
the world has to know about this you
know and uh what you what you're doing I
mean number one you come on the show I
think it was back in either late
November or early December and you give
us the news about making these Holograms
using a laser pointer which was
incredible news now here it is within
several months uh you've got another
story and another finding that you've
done that uh
if it doesn't blow anybody away then
there made out of stone or something
well too bad I can't get a patent on it
yeah
still not making any money but that's
okay
well
who knows what it'll lead to eventually
someday that's true and it you you as
far as I'm concerned it's the most
exciting time in holography for me for
years and years you know I mean I'm
addicted to it and in fact you must be
addicted too because I remember you
telling me you were going off on another
project I know and then here you are
back in again so it must be very
addictive I know I can't get away from
it yeah I keep thinking of all these
things I want to try especially the um
the two lacer thing with the electric
supply that you have oh yeah yeah I'm
really curious about that yeah wouldn't
that be something and then what you
could do if that works then you can use
one for the reference game and the other
for the object games yeah and then
because of the coherent link
uh you don't have any pathway problems
you're home free yeah and for anyone
who's listening Steve and I sent a
couple emails back
and I had suggested now I don't know
whether this is going to work or not but
uh
has things in the past have shown us you
can't always believe the things that
we've been hearing uh with traditional
holography anymore those things are
flowing by the wayside left and right
here as Steve is showing us time after
time here but running two laser pointers
but running them off of the same power
supply which splits the exact current up
into two separate currents so that the
diode is running at the same current
level and perhaps you can use one diode
for the reference beam and the other
diode for the object beam now did you
maintain any specific object to
reference ratios with this transmission
hologram I know sometimes people go four
to one or two to one some things like
that six to eight to one sometimes yeah
um were you concerned at all with that
or just set up and shooting I always try
to get as close to two to one yeah or
less but I think this particular setting
was approximately probably three to one
maybe even four to one yeah yeah and I
was amazed at the price well the person
that you had mentioned with that
infinitive pointer I think him and his
son
send you the chess piece no they didn't
well I'll pop that on the email and send
it to you because I have the chess piece
oh okay and you can see the Hologram
that they did it's a beautiful whole
Grant and the guy wrote an email you may
not find this nice enough to use and I
took a look at it and I said you've got
to be kidding me this is beautiful oh so
he wrote to you yeah oh okay yeah I've
been you know what happens with a lot of
people they go through the websites a
lot of times and they send identical
emails to a lot of different people all
the time happens all the time A lot of
times the emails that I get I know
you're getting the same ones you know
when I try to answer them and I know
you're probably answering them but
that's what they do and a lot of other
ones don't even bother on the websites
at all they just go onto the website
look for an email link click one and say
we're trying to make a hologram and we
haven't been successful we're not we
don't have an image what are we doing
wrong right and how can you answer that
I mean you need money could you please
send me a little more information and
maybe I can troubleshoot this for you
really but anyway thank I don't want to
hold you up too long because I know it's
around dinner time but I just had to
call you this is an unscheduled call an
unscheduled show but this news believe
me uh Steve this is just fantastic news
yeah I was very happy yeah I bet that'll
work I'll be checking in later in the
week and towards the end of next week to
log on and see if we can't uh get a
little peek at that uh yeah I'm just
hoping that I can get in focus of that
back wall yeah
I don't have any idea how my exposure is
going to run on that yeah well you you
know you probably know that the Hologram
itself does have depth of field just
like if the actual object were there too
right right yeah so I'm not gonna you
know if I use an F-16 on my camera I'm
not even going to cover that 24 inches I
know so I'm gonna have to make one
exposure in the front of the Hologram
yeah
Focus to the back isn't that something
was there anything on the wall what is
it like a cinder block wall actually
there's two things you see the tape you
see you see part of a mirror Mount that
I have on the table
which is about a foot away from the wall
and then you see the actual uh shadow of
the mirror on the wall oh my goodness so
hopefully I can Define that in the
photographs if not then I'll just show
the front of the lunar lander scene in
the back of the room I understand okay
which is 24 inches that's enough yeah
well well thanks for take a couple
minutes and tune on listen to the show
and
let's just keep moving ahead well we
will it makes you wonder what's next I
know what's next it's exciting all right
Steve take care okay I'll send you that
uh little chess piece that that guy sent
me I'll text you to an email jpeg all
right bye